<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copye of a verye fyne and vvytty letter sent from the ryght reuerende Levves Lippomanns byshop of Verona in Italy, and late legate in Polone, from the moste holy and blessed father Pope Paule the fourth, and from his most holy sea of Rome. Translated out of the Italyan language by Michael Throckmerton</title>
            <author>Lippomano, Luigi, 1500-1559.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843664</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843664</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05572)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 712:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copye of a verye fyne and vvytty letter sent from the ryght reuerende Levves Lippomanns byshop of Verona in Italy, and late legate in Polone, from the moste holy and blessed father Pope Paule the fourth, and from his most holy sea of Rome. Translated out of the Italyan language by Michael Throckmerton</title>
                  <author>Lippomano, Luigi, 1500-1559.</author>
                  <author>Throckmorton, Michael. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. vn der Erve],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Curtigiane of Rome [i.e. Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1556.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Written to "Peter Conterinia, gentylman of venece, at Rome".--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalog.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Considerable print show-through; leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8411:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8411:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Copye of a verye fyne and vvytty letter ſent from the ryght Reuerende Levves Lippomanus byſhop of Verona in Italy, and late Legate in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, from the moſte holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed father Pope Paule the fourth, and from his moſte holy ſea of Rome.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Italyan lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage by Michael Throckmerton.</p>
            <p>Curtigiane of Rome. 1556.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8411:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THis letter of the byſhop of Verona ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle Reader, though it be ſhort in wordes, yet if thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider it wel, it is long &amp; pitthy in matter. For it plainly diſplayeth the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes not onely of the Popiſſhe Prelates, wherby they haue procured and propped vp their kyngdome ſo longe to continue, and what deuiſes they haue to make it (if it poſſibly might be) euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng: but alſo of all other wicked that ſeke em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and glory in this world, not caring nor paſſing how vniuſtly they come by it. But God (againſt whoſe glory, this kingdome of Antichriſt is no leſſe contrary than the kingdome of the deuill him ſelf, and who wil not the euyll to come by, or at the leaſte long enioy hys deſyre) myndeth, as thou maiſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, thend of this wicked kingdom of Antichriſt and wold that al other wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s purpoſes ſhuld be letted. For he maketh (as thou ſeeſt, the ſubtile, maugre their teeth) to open their owne ſubtiltie, &amp; the wicked to vttre his own wickednes, ſo that kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wing the one, thou mayſt eaſily iudge al. Wherfore if thou wilt not ſhew thy ſelfe ouermuche ingrate, thou arte prouoked to confeſſe his greate mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his poore ſhepe, and to praiſe him for his loue and fauour toward thee. And onleſſe the nobilitie and people in euery countrey will ſhewe them ſelfe vtterly voyd of reaſon, they wyl (now God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon) put to their handes &amp; wittes to pul their nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes from vnder the tyranny of the biſhop of Rome, God and mans enemy) and ſuch wicked practiſers &amp; not willingly put their owne neckes into halter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but rather defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, according to Godd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> law, &amp; the law of nature, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſuffre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be wilfully murthered. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e God for his gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhut not thine eies againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſerue him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8411:2"/>he will not faile the in thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but proſper what ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer thou ſhalt take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, hauing his feare &amp; glorye before thyne eies.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the moſt reuerende Reynold Cardinall Pole Legate a Latere, Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhop of Cantor. Portionare of VVyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter &amp;c. Metropolitane and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of all Englande.</head>
            <p>ALbeit I doubt not but your grace procedeth in ordinarye pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe as other your complices &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>legees doo, for the maintenanes &amp; proppyng vp of your prelacy &amp; Papiſtical kyngdom, yet I thought good to aduertiſe your grace by this traſlated letter folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the practiſe &amp; proceding of your very fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop of Verons, legate in Polone, who although he hath had ſiniſtre ſucceſſe in the Popes affaires in that realme by reaſon of ouerlerned Princes, &amp; men of ouer muche er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce in prelates practiſes, yet if his tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted frendes had not diſcloſed his ſecretes, there had ben better hope of his enterpriſe. And nowe lyke as the diſplayeng of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes in ſundry tongues hath diſſolued his doinges, and marred the Popes market for euer, not onely in Polone and Pruſia, but alſo in ſondry other places and dominions where this practiſe is bruted, and no hope of
<pb facs="tcp:8411:3"/>redreſſe, onles bribing helpe, ſo muſt your grace with the reſt of your Engliſhe prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vſe faire woordes, familiar entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and liberalitie towardes the nobles of Englande in tyme, and yet where bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynge and bealycheare wyll not ſerue, you muſt take occaſion by one pretenſe or other to go in, as ye haue wil begon, in chopping of theyr heades, and hangyng vp for holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes of the ſuſpected fauourers of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and as nere as ye may, make the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe bloude thynne, namelye the gentil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and riche people, ſo that when they are ones pulled vnder foote, ye maye pyll and ſubdue the commons at your pleaſure and tranſpoſe the realme as ye luſte. And as I dour not the experienced dexteritie of your handlyng the popes affaires in England in bryngyng the realme into hunger, miſery, and diſſencion, ſo were it to be wyſhed that your Prelates and vnſkilled cleargye in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, wer inſtructed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyke practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with all ſilence and ſecrecy, leaſt the vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of hypocriſy beyng plucked of (as the byſhop of Veronas vnlucky chaunce was, and your brybynge and bloudſheadyng co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng ones to lyght cauſe further peryll to your ſtates than hytherto hath ben felt.</p>
            <p>The God of al mercy and might confound all falſe and wicked practyſyng. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your graces moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſeruant M. Th.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8411:3"/>
            <head>To the ryght honourable may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Peter Conterini, gentylman of Venece, at Rome</head>
            <p>RYghte honourable ſyr, I haue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tymes ſyth it hath pleaſed god to trouble me by makynge me to take in hand this enterpriſe of Polone wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to your honour, as to one that both for countreyes ſake, and for our olde acquian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and alſo for his goodnes doth vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſafe to bee my father and protectour in my great tormentes and troubles, wherin I haue ben wrapped, prayeng you always that it woulde pleaſe you to ayde me with youre authoritie (whyche is ſo greate with our holy fathers holmes) that I may be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to come out of this helle, and retourne to Rome, or to my church. But all the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles paſte are nothyng in reſpecte of thoſe that I ſuffer at this preſente, the whiche I can not but write vnto you, to thintent that your honour vnderſtanding it, may be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to haue compaſſion on my miſfortune, and to doo your vttermoſt to cauſe me to be called home, whiche I beſeeche you on my knees liftyng vp my handes. The new tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiles wherof I write vnto you be theſe.</p>
            <p>The lord Nicholas Raduil Counte Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latin of Vilna is doubtles one of the greteſt
<pb facs="tcp:8411:4"/>men of power &amp; authoritie within all the realme of Polone. And as he is alſo one of the chiefeſt that dothe fauour and promote the cauſe of the Lutheria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo he ſhulde not be. Nowe I being ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of nature &amp; ſure iudgement y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can not (I can not, I ſay) ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt holy ſea apoſtolike of Rome ſhulde be thus re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in pieces &amp; railed on; as I ſee it euery daye rent &amp; railed on in dede, I determined with my ſelfe no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to diſſemble, but to pull of my viſour, and to write vnto this lorde a playne letter of my mynde without reſpecte.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe to colour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, I fayned, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one M. Adam Conarſkye ſecretary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge, had ſaluted me by his letters, &amp; had reherſed many frendely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des on the behalf of his lordſhip. And vpon this occaſion I began my letter, whereyng my wittes, &amp; makynge it as earneſt and as piththy as I coulde poſſible: and I ſente it hym the. <hi>21.</hi> of February, at whiche time I was at a caſtell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> archbiſhop of Gnezna called Louitz, where I alſo am at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Theffect of this letter was, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed this lorde Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Palatine, how tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the hole realme it was comonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that his lordſhip agreed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therians in all pointes. And I began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſe theym vnto him particularly one by one. And in the ende I exhorted him to giue
<pb facs="tcp:8411:4"/>ouer &amp; leaue theſe hereticall opinions, for otherwiſe God woulde puniſſhe hym. The truth is, I touched all the hole rable of the Lutherans, and ſpake of their doinges, as muche as the greate and inwarde hatred I beare them could eryreſſe. For in dede ther is none euill, but it maye be well ſpoken of thoſe villaines. This lord the Counte Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, who I thought ſeinge my letters ſo true and ſo wel proued with good reaſons, ſhuld haue bene pulled from his practiſyng with the Lutherans, made me ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer (right honorable M. Petre) as Martin Luther him ſelfe wold not haue done, I do not ſay, vnto a man in my ſtate (which am neuertheles a miniſter &amp; legate, albeit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of our holy fathers holyneſſe, &amp; of his moſt holy ſea of Rome) but not to any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man perſon wer he neuer ſo vile &amp; miſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. I would haue ſent your honour a copy of the ſame anſwer, but to tell you the truth me thought it wold ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to our very great ſhame, if it ſhould he redde. And therfore I tremble for very feare, leaſt by one meanes or other it will be put foorthe in print, and perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce tranſlated into diuers tongues. For I knowe the caſte of theſe heretykes wherwith God is not pleaſed. But it maye pleaſe your honour to heare the teſt.</p>
            <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n I was in the yeare. <hi>1548.</hi> ioyned in commiſſion with the moſt Reuerende than
<pb facs="tcp:8411:5"/>biſhop of Fano now worthyly a Cardinal &amp; with the Reuerend of good memory, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentinus our holy fathers nuncio or legate in Germany, after the victory that thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror had ouer the proteſtances, to bryng and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princis &amp; people to the obedience of the ſea apoſtolike (for ſo was the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our ambaſſade, albeit it ſucceded not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proſperouſly, &amp; we reconciled very few) there wer at that tyme priſoners to thempe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rors maieſty Iohn Friderike, Duke &amp; Cur fuſter of Saxonie, &amp; Philip Landtgraue of Heſſe. Than I with my right reuerend-col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legues, as obedient children, accordyng to our inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s gaue counſell to themperor and his moſt noble brother the kyng of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, that they ſhuld cauſe thoſe two prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces heades to be openly cut of, as the ring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leaders and mainteynours of heretikes.</p>
            <p>For by this meanes and with this terrour an ende at length ſhould haue ben made of all hereſies in Germanye. But their maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties thought it not beſt to folow ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and therefore, the matters of the ſea Apoſtolike be in that countrey as they be: that is, they were neuer in worſe caſe, and I ſee, they wyll be euery day worſe &amp; worſe. And I hauyng the like commiſſion at this preſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out moſt holy father pope Paul the fourthe, haue often geuen counſaile to this moſt noble king of Polone, exhortyng
<pb facs="tcp:8411:5"/>him that he wold cauſe to be cut of .viii. or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heades of the moſt chiefe of thoſe that go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſtirre vp this doctrine of the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans in Polone: For this is the right way to kepe the realme cleane from hereſies</p>
            <p>It is true, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel to the Kinges maieſtie, &amp; I haue vttred it vnto one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is in great authoritie w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> him, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he ſhuld helpe to perſuade him. Nowe ſuche a matter of ſo great importance which wold haue ben kepte ſo ſecrete as euer any was, leaſt it ſhuld brede more enuy &amp; batred vnto the moſt holy vicars of Chriſt, ſuche a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I ſay, I feare it be diſcloſed &amp; opened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode in euery corner. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid lord Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Palatine hath laid it to my charge by his letters: &amp; haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g writen it, it is no doubt but he hath ſpoken it, &amp; wil ſpeke it vnto others.</p>
            <p>Now pleſeth it your honor to conſider, in what caſe I ſtande, and of what mynde I maye be, and whether I haue reaſonable cauſe to deſire to be diſpatched he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Thoſe that be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promoters of theſe hereſies be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny &amp; mighty. I haue done what I coulde to ridde the world of them. Truly ther hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no lack on my behalf. What think you thei wil do towards me if I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in their eies? I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loke for non other tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned curſed railed &amp; cried out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if no wors hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greueth me moſt, that they wil go about to ſprede horrible tales abrode
<pb facs="tcp:8411:6"/>againſt our holy fathers holineſſe, not only in Polone, but alſo throughout al Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; wyl ſaye, as their maner is, that theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels that his holynes wil make: that is, with choppynge of heades, &amp; other ſuch like violences: Yea I vnderſtand they ſpeake it all redy, and wonderfully blow it abrode: wherby I doo perceiue a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; hurt to the doing of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt Reuerend and noble Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Caraffa hath lately co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto me by his letters, that is, to let them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that this their deſire to make a natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall councel, is a part and paint of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. And that therfore they ſpeake not nor thinke therof, but cary for a general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, which his holynes wyl ſhortly make. I ſay in this now am I altogyther occupied, and I thought I myght haue don ſome good in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eferrynge and prolongynge the tyme, as his holynes deſyre is: but the matter beyng diſcloſed (as I haue ſayd before) I can not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but al men be againſt me, no man wyl here me, all mens myndes are alienate from me and vtterly ſet againſt me. In ſomuch (to be ſhort) wer it not for theſe moſt reuerend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſpecially this moſt Reuerend father, the ſaid Archbiſhop, who is my ſainctuary, I could not tell where to ſaue my lyfe, they ſpeake ſo muche euyl of me. And whan thei haue nothyng to talk of, than they go about
<pb facs="tcp:8411:6"/>ſaying, thei know for what cauſe I can not be made cardinal: as thogh I ſhuld be agry with God for that it hath pleſed him I ſhuld be born out of lauful matrimony. I am con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it hath pleſed him to make me to be born a chriſten man, and therfore I paſſe not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that other. But this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth me excedyngly to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that ther goth about a certain letter printed in diuers tongues, wherein bicauſe I was aſſiſtent to the moſt reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of good memory Cardinall Creſcentius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Legate in the councel of Trent, al thyng is imputed to me &amp; my counſel that was done in the ſame councel of Trent, and ſpecially that audience was not geuen to the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, as in dede it was not mete nor ought to be. For I confeſſe, that I haue alwayes ben of this opinion, that he which is out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, ought not to be admitted to ſpeak of matters of the churche. But thoſe that vnderſtand it on the contrary part, whan I ſhall ſpeake any more of the holdynge of a generall councell, will out of all peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſay to my face, that we mynd to make it ſuche a Councel as he counſailed &amp; labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to be don at Tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: that is not to here the other parte. Your honour with your noble brethern M. Franciſce (the light of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon welth of Venece) and M. Paule made ſo much of, and gaue ſo muche honor vnto our holy fathers holynes, when he was a
<pb facs="tcp:8411:7"/>barefooted Frier at Venece, that his holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes beyng moſt myndfull and thankfull I knowe, is deſirous alſo to requite and doo you pleaſure agayne. Wherfore I hartily beſeche your honour let it ſtande with your pleaſure to beſtowe one droppe of the fauor that ye are in, and cauſe me to bee rydde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t of theſe troubles and daungers. And it may pleaſe his holynes to vnderſtand, that it is to no purpoſe for me to haue the doyng of thynges here any longer, for the greate hatred that I haue already purchaſed me. Let his holynes conſyder whether it be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſend one to ſupply my place, or to leue this realme without any Legate, which in myne opinion were beſt, bicauſe he can not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e here any longer with honor &amp; eſtimation</p>
            <p>Moreouer I think, that when that ſhalbe done, and is done, yet theſe men wil haue it after their owne fantaſy, and there wyll be agreat ſciſme, ſo that the nobilitie will fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one way and one doctrine, and the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops an other. And yet I can tell you, not all the byſhops, for one part of them begyn to halte, and a lyttel thyng will make them agree with the Counte Palatine (of whom I write) and the others. But lette his holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doo, as it pleaſeth hym, in ſendynge or not ſendyng an other Legate to ſupply my place, ſo he diſpatche me hence, &amp; that quick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. Who can ſee, who can ſuffer, that at the
<pb facs="tcp:8411:7"/>Shroftide, diſguyſynges, maſkes, &amp; mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meries of monkes, fryers, and Cardinals, ſhuide be openly made, to the open ſhame &amp; reproche of all the hole order of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, as there hath ben here in my time? And who can diſgeſt theſe troubles, theſe villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and not thynke vppon the daunger of his lyfe? Muche good doo it hym: ſurely I aknowlage my ſelfe to be a manne that can not doo it. And I haue no hope that I ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be hable hereafter to do any good here. To be playn I haue done as muche as was poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible for me to doo, to lette the diet and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſhalbe kept at Bartilmew tide: But yet notwithſtandynge it will procede. Neither ſhal it auaile to waſt my braines &amp; deſtroy my body, ſuffring my ſelf to be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t from place to place in Couche, in company of the ſaid moſt reuerende Archbiſhop tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all the greater and the leſſe Polone, and ſo to haue brought to paſſe, that the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble kyng hath geuen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the determinacion &amp; concluſion of the laſt parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as I aduertiſed our holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers holy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great grudging of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. Beſides I fear leſt theſe felowes ſhal cauſe men to come out of Germany, &amp; ſpecially out of Schwitzerland half a doſin of the greateſt clerkes &amp; moſt famous diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be ther, bicauſe it is bruced abrode, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Pope mynded to ſende of his diuines
<pb facs="tcp:8411:8"/>to this parliament to defend our cauſe. And all be it I haue bothe ſayd and earneſtly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in euery place, that they ſhulde not thinke, that his holynes will euer ſende or conſent to any ſuch parliament, which ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be none other but a nationall councell. Yet neuertheles as farre as I can vnderſtand, they mynd to cauſe of our enemies, diuine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of other contreys to come hither: Your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may conſider, what confections theſe men wil make, and what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſultations and concluſions they wyll determyne agaynſts vs. God helpe vs, for I ſe the matters be in a very evyll caſe. I recommende me vnto your honor.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours ſeruant Ludouicus Lippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus byſhop of Verona, the vnvvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye Legate.</signed> 
               <dateline>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Louitz <date>the. <hi>20.</hi> of Iuly. <hi>56.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcripte.</head>
            <p>I Am aboute to make a Conuocation of all the byſhoppes and prelates of this Realm, and wyll begyn it now in <hi>Petricouia.</hi> Two thinges I hope I ſhall obteyn there, the one to gather a great ſumme of money, and I truſt the popes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes wyll be a contributour vnto it (for to hath he put me in hope) wherby we may be better able to defend our matters, aboue all thynges contentyng theim, and ſtoppynge their mouthes which be importunately bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and make muche troub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e us aboo. And
<pb facs="tcp:8411:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e haue ofte proued, that this practiſe is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y good way: The ſeconde, that there be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me correction of lyfe of the cleargy, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he playne are a very euyl example. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s miſchief is, that the reformation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers is at this preſent to lyttell purpoſe, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſerue our high eſtate and authorite, For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe curſed Heretikes pretende and crye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at the doctrine muſt be corrected. As for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ample: they be not contente that the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s ſhulde be honeſt wyſe, and diſcrete, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey wyll haue the maſſe al togither hurled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aye. Nother are they contented, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ope ſhuld be a modeſt man and of a vertu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s lyfe, and that he ſhuld not receyue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y for ſpiritual thyngs, but they wyl, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere ſhoulde be no Pope nother good nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dde. This is the pricke, this is the marke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey ſhoote at. I ſay, we are in an euyl caſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>The xxij. of Iulye.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The ſame. L. Lippomanus. Legate.</head>
            <p>I Haue this daye receaued lettres fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Venece, whiche haue encreaced ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe vpon ſorowe. For one my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frende, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yteth vnto me, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te of the ſeruice, which I haue don here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d of the contencions that I haue founde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe partes, chiefly with the ſayd Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Palatine, comming to the eares of myne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uorable lordes of Venece, their honours
<pb facs="tcp:8411:9"/>be very ſory complaine and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>f of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayeng, that they be afraid, leaſt I bey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a Venecian, and of the bloud I am of, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Alemaines and poleakes will beleue, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the lordes of Venece them ſelues conſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my doinges, wherby thei may herea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bee partakers of the ſame hatred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they goe about to ſtere againſt the Pope and perhappes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at one tyme or at an othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſelf ſame daungers. And to ſaye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth, theſe men ſpread abroade very mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> how becauſe I am a venecian, all thynge pleaſe the venecians that I do, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would not doo it, if I knewe it ſhoulde di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleaſe their honours.</p>
            <p>To conclude, for all reſpectes, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uancement of the cauſe and maters of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holy fathers holynes, for not encombrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of my lordes of Venece with theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the ſuretie of my life, it ſhal be wel do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to call we away hence. I wold gladly ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ben called away by ſom other meanes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with ſome other honour: but pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ience, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges be at ſuch a poynte, that I muſt thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon my lyfe, and not vpon honour. I ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lacke none hereafter, if I can eſcape hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with life. Yet eftſones I commende me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to your honour. The xxii. of Iulye.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The ſame Levvis Lippoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us Legate.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8411:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
